<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Optus Networks Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd (No. 2) (includes Corrigendum dated 7 July 2009) [2009] FCA 422 (9 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/422.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 976">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 976">application for further and better discovery and production</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 976">where applicant also commenced related proceedings in hong kong</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 976">whether applicant obligated to discover and produce documents filed in or related to those proceedings including witness statements</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 976">applicant obliged to comply with processes in this jurisdiction notwithstanding the implied undertaking as to discovery in the hong kong proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">restrictive trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">accessorial liability for contravention of s 45e(3) of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">existence of an "arrangement or understanding"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">lack of necessary "meeting of the minds" evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">admissibility under s 45 of the evidence act 1995 (cth) of document witness taken to in cross-examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">admissibility of witness statement where witness not called</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 678">admissibility of answers to s 155 trade practices act 1974 (cth) notices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">advice privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">litigation privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">implied undertaking</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">public interest immunity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">work product</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">draft witness statements and witness proofs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">whether filing and service, without more, of witness statements constitutes waiver of privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">distinction between privilege and implied undertaking</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">whether encouragement of cartel whistleblowers by protecting confidentiality of statements made to investigators presents a real public interest where there is no evidence that confidentiality was sought or that whistleblowers would be deterred from coming forward by lack of confidentiality</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">whether public regulatory agency's interest in guarding its work product presents a cognisable public interest</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 88">whether work product doctrine has a separate existence from legal professional privilege in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">1. leave be granted to the applicants to file in court an amended notice of motion moving the court for a further, or alternative, order that leave be granted to the applicants for the use of pars 86</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">93 and 166</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">177 of, and attachments 'sl8-c' and 'sl26-c' to the lee outline (as referred to in orders made by this court on 26 july 1996 in proceedings no. 731 of 1995). 2. leave be granted to the applicants to file and serve a second further amended application and third consolidated amended statement of claim substantially in the form of the documents reproduced at pages 15</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">148 of exhibit beh-2 to the affidavit of bruce eric hambrett sworn 8 may 2006. 3. leave be granted to the applicants for the use of pars 86</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">93 and 166</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 1752">177 of, and attachments 'sl8-c' and 'sl26-c' to the lee outline (as referred to in orders made by this court on 26 july 1996 in proceedings no. 731 of 1995).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">implied waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">issue waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">whereprivilege-holder acts inconsistently with the privilege by putting the contents of otherwise privileged documents in issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">commissioner of taxation identified bases for satisfaction and exercises of discretion as matters evidenced in these documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.7" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 86">test of waiver of privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 3">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 3">affidavit sworn, filed and served in first proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 3">leave to use the affidavit in later proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 3">affidavit not privileged</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 3">leave to use granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">waiver</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">letter conveying substance and effect of legal advice to third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">inconsistency between disclosure and confidentiality</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">waiver imputed where final conclusion of legal advice stated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">voluntary disclosure of the conclusion of legal advice waives privilege in relation to undisclosed reasons for conclusion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">disclosure of one conclusion does not necessarily waive privilege in relation to undisclosed conclusions  freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">appeal from administrative appeals tribunal on question of law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">exempt documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">documents privileged from production on grounds of legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">principles relating to waiver of privilege in documents otherwise exempt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">decision as to waiver involved an error on a question of law as to correct application of test for waiver of privilege freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.14" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.15" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">powers of tribunal under freedom of information act 1982 (cth) s 58</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.16" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">tribunal empowered to review any decision made by an agency or minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.17" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">tribunal stands in shoes of relevant agency or minister for purpose of administrative review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.18" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">power of tribunal to review decision of agency or minister not severable from power to determine threshold questions in relation to reviewable decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.19" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">tribunal not empowered to review decision to claim exemption from disclosure on grounds of privilege without reviewing validity of privilege claim itself freedom of information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.20" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">exempt documents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.21" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">documents privileged from production on grounds of legal professional privilege</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.22" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">documents containing privileged matter not exempt if used by relevant agency to determine entitlements or obligations of persons generally under an enactment or scheme administered by that agency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.23" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">legal advice provided in relation to particular case may fall within this category in some circumstances administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.24" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 237">limits upon power of court on appeal from administrative appeals tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">high court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">practice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">further discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">when ordered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[1959] HCA 23">rules of the high court, o. 32, rr. 13, 18.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">categories of discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether discovery sought by both parties appropriate given pleadings and prior findings of the court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether discovery by the applicant at this stage of the proceedings premature</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">affidavit of disclosure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 485">whether affidavit of disclosure appropriate in addition to discovery by respondent in circumstances where discovery concerns extent of liability and form and quantum of pecuniary relief.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 21">equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 21">duty of confidentiality</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 21">confidential information defined in agreement between parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCAFC 21">whether concurrent equitable obligations exist   cases cited: attorney-general v jonathan cape ltd [1976] qb 752 cited australian medic-care co ltd v hamilton pharmaceuticals pty ltd (2009) 261 alr cited</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 485">Relevantly for present purposes, my reasons for judgment in [2009] FCA 422 ('reasons for judgment') contain the following observations and findings: 
 
 '[8] Where the telecommunications networks of two carriers are interconnected, and telecommunications traffic generated by customers of one carrier passes across the network operated by the other carrier, the latter carrier has access to certain information relating to that telecommunications traffic. This includes information regarding the quantity, source, destination, duration, time of occurrence or kind of the telecommunications traffic, as well as the value of the telecommunications traffic whether in terms of its aggregate billing value or individual customer billing details and value (collectively, 'traffic information'). 
 

 
 
 [9] For a particular telephone call such traffic information could include: 
 

 
 
 (1) Quantity - the number or volume of calls made;
 (2) source --- the telephone number of the customer making the call and the geographic location from which the call was made;
 (3) destination --- the telephone number and the geographic location to which the call was made; 
 (4) duration --- the length of the call in time;
 (5) time of occurrence --- the date and time at which the call took place;
 (6) kind --- such as whether the call was a long distance call or was made using different telecommunications services; and
 (7) value --- the amount to be billed for that call or for that part of the call carried by the carrier. The discovery that is now sought from each party by the other, follows findings of the respondent's ('Telstra's') liability for breach of provisions of the Access Agreement to which the applicant ('Optus') and Telstra are parties ([2009] FCA 422 and [2009] FCA 728) and for breach of Telstra's duty of confidence to Optus ([2010] FCAFC 21). On 21 November 2007 I ordered that certain issues be reserved for separate and later determination pursuant to O 29 r 2 of the Federal Court Rules (Cth) ('Rules'). The discovery now sought concerns those reserved issues --- Optus' entitlement to relief, the quantum of any pecuniary relief, including the extent of Telstra's use of confidential information by the preparation and distribution of market share reports to officers of Telstra for certain specific purposes. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCAFC 21">25 On 30 April 2009 the primary judge upheld Optus' claim in contract: Optus Networks Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd (No 2) [2009] FCA 422. On 10 July 2009 his Honour dismissed its claims in equity and under s 51AA of the Trade Practices Act : Optus Networks Ltd v Telstra Corporation Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 728. On 4 September 2009 he ordered that on all issues other than those reserved for later determination, judgment be entered on the contract claim based on findings that:
 
 
 (a) [Telstra] used information which is traffic information ... which is also Confidential Information of [Optus] for the purposes of clause 1.1 of the Access Agreement ... or Communication Information of [Optus] for the purposes of clause 1.1 of the Access Agreement otherwise subject to the requirements of confidentiality in clause 15 of the Access Agreement. (b) [Telstra] breached clause 15.2 of the Access Agreement by: 
 
 
 
 (i) using Traffic Information from the NUMIS 100 system to prepare weekly STD and IDD market share reports ('Market Share Reports');
 (ii) insofar as the Market Share Reports contain Traffic Information, being Confidential Information or Communication Information of [Optus] ..., distributing the Market Share Reports among [Telstra's] personnel; and
 (iii) insofar as the Market Share Reports contain Traffic Information, being Confidential Information or Communication Information of [Optus] ..., using one or more of the Market Share Reports for the purpose of: 
 
 
 
 
 (A) marketing, including considering or developing strategy for marketing, products or services of [Telstra] to existing or prospective customers; or
 (B) promotion, including considering or developing strategy for promotion, of products or services of [Telstra] to existing or prospective customers; or
 (C) selling, including considering or developing strategy for selling, products or services of [Telstra] to existing or prospective customers. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 122 Loss of client legal privilege: consent and related matters</title>
<title id="l2">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1997 </title>
<title id="l3">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1997 - SECT 137 Protection from civil proceedings</title>
<title id="l4">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 </title>
<title id="l5">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 No. 98 of 1991 - SECT 51 AUSTEL not otherwise subject to government direction</title>
<title id="l6">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 No. 98 of 1991 - SECT 88 Carriers' employees etc. not to disclose or use contents of communications etc.</title>
<title id="l7">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT 1991 No. 98 of 1991 - SECT 137 Right to interconnection and related carriage</title>
</legistitles>
</case>