<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>VIP Plastic Packaging Pty Ltd v B.M.W. Plastics Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 593 (2 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/593.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">infringement proceedings pursuant to s 120 patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where applicants proprietors of patent for membranous termite barrier</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where first and second respondents manufactured, sold, installed, offered for sale or installation, advertised, promoted and marketed termite barrier system</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where third respondents authorised, procured and directed such conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether permissible to construe independent claims in patent by reference to subsequent dependent claims</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether respondents infringed applicant's patent. held: infringement turns on a comparison between the applicants' patent and respondents' product</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">subsequent dependent claim no assistance in interpretation of independent claims in circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">respondents' product contains all integers in claims of applicants' patent alleged to be infringed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">respondents infringed applicants' patent. intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">counter-claim for revocation of patent pursuant to s 121 patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where applicants proprietor of patent for membranous termite barrier</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where combination patent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">where prior art information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.16" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether invention embodied in patent a patentable invention within s 18 patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.17" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether prior art anticipates invention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.18" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether invention lacks novelty within s 7(1) patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.19" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether prior patents or patent applications part of common general knowledge within s 7(2) patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.20" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether invention was obvious within s 7(2) patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.21" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether invention lacks inventive step within s 7(2) patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.22" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">whether invention is useful within s 18(1)(c) patents act 1990 (cth). held: no prior art information anticipated invention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.23" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">invention taken to be novel</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.24" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">evidence does not establish prior patents and patent applications part of common general knowledge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.25" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">invention not obvious</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.26" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">invention taken to involve inventive step</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.27" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">invention embodied in patent properly construed useful</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.28" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">invention embodied in patent a patentable invention</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.29" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">patent valid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.30" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 1493">counter-claim dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">patents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">amendment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">obviousness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">novelty</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">post-grant re-examination by commissioner of patents pursuant to request made by third party under s 97(2) of the patents act 1990 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">commissioner required by s 98 to report on whether invention not novel and whether invention did not involve inventive step, when compared with prior art base as it existed before priority date, excluding information made publicly available only through the doing of an act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">third party requesting re-examination by commissioner required by reg 9.2 of patents regulations 1991 (cth) to identify documents on basis of which third party asserts any claim not novel or does not involve inventive step</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">how test of obviousness to be applied on ex parte re-examination under s 97(2), without evidence as to whether person skilled in the relevant art would have ascertained, understood and regarded as relevant the information in the documents identified by the third party in its request</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">'onus'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">whether evidence required</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">nature of re-examination under s 97(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">whether amendment is part of re-examination process</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">whether decision on application for leave to amend must be made before decision to revoke</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">whether commissioner at liberty simply to decide to revoke on assumption specification amended as requested</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2005] FCA 996">tests for allowable amendments.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2009] APO 18">In this regard the considerations seem to be not unlike those that apply where the Court has been requested to exercise its discretion to direct re-examination under s97(3). These have been given judicial consideration including most recently in VIP Plastic Packaging Pty Ltd v B.M.W Plastics Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 593 where Justice Kenny found at [16]:
 
"I doubt that the provision of a report by the Commissioner after re-examination would reduce the cost of this proceeding and expedite its determination. First, the Commissioner's report after re-examination is not binding on the Court. In the absence of an undertaking of the kind sought by B.M.W. Generally the Commissioner only re-examines an application where she becomes aware of information on which she is satisfied that the patent granted would be clearly invalid ( Commissioner of Patents v Emperor Sports Pty Ltd [2005] FCA 996). Normally this occurs in circumstances where, save the re-examination action by the Commissioner, grant of a potentially invalid patent will follow as a matter of course. In this light, re-examination in the context of an existing opposition is clearly a special case and the considerations are not unlike those that apply where the Court has been requested to exercise its discretion to direct re-examination under s97(3) as in VIP plastic Packaging Pty Ltd v B.M.W Plastics Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 593. On this basis it is apparent that in the circumstances the public interest predominantly lies in the expeditious determination of the opposition on its merits. Re-examination may assist in resolving or reducing the cost of opposition and there is some prospect of this, for example, where the parties agree that re-examination occur.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">PATENTS ACT 1990 </title>
<title id="l1">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 7 Novelty and inventive step</title>
<title id="l2">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 97 Re-examination of complete specifications</title>
<title id="l3">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 98 Report on re-examination</title>
<title id="l4">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 99 Statement by applicant or patentee</title>
<title id="l5">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 100 Copies of report to be given to court</title>
<title id="l6">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 101 Revocation of patent--re-examination after grant</title>
<title id="l7">PATENTS ACT 1990 - SECT 138 Revocation of patents in other circumstances</title>
<title id="l8">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>