<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 (5 June 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/606.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">deceptive similarity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">whether aural use of 'crazy ron' infringed a registered composite trade mark which included the words 'crazy john'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">whether 'crazy john' an essential feature of the registered markintellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">registration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">amendment of particulars of application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 196">whether s 65(5) of the trade marks act 1995 (cth) authorises amendment of an application which names the wrong person as the owner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">ingredients</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">questions of fact</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">relevance of "fraud" in the form of an intention to misappropriate rival trader's reputation as evidence from which an intention to deceive others and the likelihood of that deception may be inferred</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">distinguished from "fraud" in a remedial context.   reckitt and colman products ltd v borden inc [1990] ukhl 12 ; (1990) 17 ipr 1</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">cons.   conagra inc v mccain foods (aust) pty ltd [1992] fca 159 ; (1992) 33 fcr 302</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">cons.   trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">consumer protection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.8" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">trade practices act 1974 ss 52 and 53</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.9" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">passing off context</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.10" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">likelihood of deception</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.11" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">questions of fact.   injunction quia timet injunction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.12" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">persistence in assertion of the right to do a thing properly objected to as a ground for the grant of a quia timet injunction.   myers v casey [1913] hca 50 ; (1913) 17 clr 90</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.13" type=cited from="[1995] FCA 1175">cons.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">bases and elements of passing off action</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">whether carrying on business within jurisdiction or place of business within jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">sufficiency of nexus with the jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">necessity and method of establishing reputation within jurisdiction</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">requirement of goodwill</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">whether fraud is a necessary element of passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">relevance of establishing fraud.  trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[1992] FCA 159">relationship between reputation in passing off action and establishing misleading and deceptive conduct.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">trademarks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">whether trade mark capable of distinguishing designated goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">geographic reference</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">description of style of goods</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">cancellation of trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">trade marks act 1995 (cth), ss 41 , 88 (2)(a), (e) torts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">whether there has been representation by the respondent to the public leading the public to believe the goods offered by the respondent are the applicant's goods trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.10" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">clear distinguishing features</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.11" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">trade practices act 1974 (cth), ss 52 , 53  evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.12" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.13" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1367">ss 60 , 136 , 190(3) evidence act 1995 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">s 52 of the trade practices act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">relevant date for the assessment of conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">conduct not held to be misleading.  tort</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">establishing a reputation or secondary meaning in the product</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">whether the promotion and supply of similar articles is likely to deceive potential purchasers to believe the rival trader's product was put out by or associated with the applicant or that the rival trader is itself associated with the applicant.  interpretation of settlement deeds and releases</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 23">matters in contemplation of parties at the time release given.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">torts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">adoption of similar get-up for enhanced water products</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">no liability where allegedly appropriated features were in common use in enhanced water market</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">adoption of features of competitors' get-up permissible where respondent's products sufficiently distinguished through branding and other means</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.6" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">no proof of relevant reputation in features allegedly appropriated</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.7" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">no proof of deception amongst ordinary reasonable consumers</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.8" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">no proof of intent to mislead</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp8.9" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 2">application dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">intellectual property</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">passing off</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">misleading and deceptive conduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">trade mark infringement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">use as a trade mark</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">distinguishing features of the maltesers get-up and trade marks</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">features commonplace in confectionary packaging</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">deceptive similarity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">imperfect recollection</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCAFC 174">descriptive words</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] ATMO 34">[11] Trade mark registration 828126 has now been removed from the register for non-payment of the renewal fee. [12] As to this, the line of authority in Australia stretches back to Southern Cross Refrigerating Co v Toowoomba Foundry Pty Ltd (1954) 92 CLR 592 at 606. Mr Heerey noted the recent convenient summary in Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 ; (2009) 81 IPR 354 at [95] . [13] [1960] HCA 47 ; (1960) 103 CLR 391 at 401. It might also be fair to observe that the breadth of the statement of goods and services in the current matter is not on all fours with Aston and that reg 4.8(3) could arguably have been applied by the examiner of trade marks.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2011] ATMO 26">Mr Williams had relied on a proposition from Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 in relation to s 44: 
A corollary appears to be that in assessing the notion of a consumer's imperfect recollection of a mark, the fact that a mark is notoriously so ubiquitous and of such long standing that consumers generally must be taken to be familiar with it and its use in relation to particular goods or services is a relevant consideration: Crazy Ron's at 232-233 [90]. The application of these principles is, so it seems to me, relatively straightforward. The Maltesers marks are very famous. Consumers generally must be taken to be familiar with them. That is relevant to assessing a consumer's imperfect recollection of the mark. So viewed, a comparison between the impression held in the consumer's mind and the direct impression of Sweet Rewards' mark is one which, in this case at least, occurs in a context in which the chances of the average consumer having forgotten the Maltesers mark are vanishingly small. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] FCA 1367">There are similarities between this case and the facts considered by the Full Courts who decided Johnson &amp; Johnson , Pepsico Australia Pty Ltd v The Kettle Chip Company Pty Ltd (1996) IPR 161 , Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 ; (2009) 81 IPR 354 and the decision of Sundberg J in Guylian . </sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 23">When viewed in light of Bodum's consistent and extensive promotion and sale over a significant duration, I have already indicated that the Bodum products must be considered to be well known and appreciated. Bodum's presence and dominance has created a situation where it is a well known brand of some level of sophistication with a separate and distinct identity from look-alike products. This separate identity---its get-up---is never isolated from the Bodum Chambord Coffee Plunger or the Bodum Assam teapot. In this sense, Bodum could be said to be 'a victim of its own success' (see Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 at [32] and (2009) FCAFC 174 at [13] ). </sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 2">Sometimes the proven circumstances may support causes of action under Pt V of the TPA (which includes ss 52 and 53 ) as well as in common law passing off. As the Court said in Cadbury Schweppes Pty Ltd v Darrell Lea Chocolate Shops Pty Ltd [2007] FCAFC 70 ; (2007) 159 FCR 397 (' Cadbury' ) at 418-419, despite their different origins and purposes, there is an overlap between these causes of action. A misrepresentation as to the source of a trader's goods is not only an element in the tort of passing off, it can also be conduct that is misleading or deceptive or likely to mislead or deceive for the purposes of s 52 of the TPA: see Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd ('Sweet Rewards') [2009] FCA 606 ; (2009) 81 IPR 354 at 360 per Perram J and Ricegrowers at 48 per Rares J. Equally, such a misrepresentation can amount to a relevant misrepresentation for the purposes of s 53(c) and (d). As the Full Court said in Cadbury at 418: 
 
 [T]rade indicia other than names and logos can become associated with a particular trader, such that a use by another trader could give rise to misleading and deceptive conduct or passing off. If particular branding elements used by a trader have been identified in a special way with that trader in the minds of members of the public, there may be misleading or deceptive conduct by reason of the appropriation of those particular branding elements by another trader. 
 
 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2009] FCAFC 174">2 Mars commenced a proceeding in the Court seeking injunctive relief and damages and other relief against Sweet Rewards. Mars contended that Sweet Rewards, by distribution and sale of its chocolate covered malt ball product:
 
&#8226; infringed the trade marks;
 
&#8226; signified and represented to consumers and traders that its product is associated with Maltesers, originates from the same source or origin as Maltesers and is associated with the source or origin of Maltesers;
 
&#8226; represented to consumers and traders that its product is associated with or has the endorsement, approval, sponsorship or licence of Mars; represents to consumers and traders that its product is made from the same ingredients as Maltesers, is made to the same recipe as Maltesers and provides the same taste and other sensory experience as Maltesers when eaten. The primary judge rejected each of the allegations. On 5 June 2009, for reasons then given, his Honour dismissed the proceeding with costs ( Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606 ; (2009) 81 IPR 354). Mars now appeals from those orders.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2009] FCA 899">On 5 June 2009 I dismissed all of Mars' claims: Mars Australia Pty Ltd v Sweet Rewards Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 606. At the time I ordered Mars to pay Sweet Rewards' costs of the proceedings. Sweet Rewards now seeks that that cost order be vacated and in its stead that there be an order that the costs be borne by Mars on an indemnity basis. </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l1">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 64 Exception: civil proceedings if maker available</title>
<title id="l2">EVIDENCE ACT 1995 - SECT 67 Notice to be given</title>
<title id="l3">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 </title>
<title id="l4">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 10 Definition of deceptively similar</title>
<title id="l5">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 17 What is a trade mark?</title>
<title id="l6">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 70 Colours in registered trade marks</title>
<title id="l7">TRADE MARKS ACT 1995 - SECT 120 When is a registered trade mark infringed?</title>
<title id="l8">EVIDENCE REGULATIONS 1995 </title>
<title id="l9">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>