<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Limited (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 (9 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/727.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">application for leave to appeal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">freezing orders granted against non-parties to the proceeding pursuant to o 25a r 2 of the federal court rules</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">principles to be followed in granting mareva relief against third parties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">primary judge addressed the correct test</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">decision not attended with sufficient doubt to warrant it being reconsidered</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">third parties would suffer no substantial injustice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 216">application dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">freezing orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">whether applicant has good arguable case on accrued cause of action against respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">whether danger prospective judgment in favour of applicants against respondents will remain unsatisfied or partly unsatisfied if recovery restricted to assets of respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">whether process is or may be available to applicants as consequence of judgment against respondents pursuant to which third party may be obliged to disgorge property or otherwise contribute to funds or property of respondents to help satisfy judgment against respondents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">where properties potential subjects of freezing orders held by third parties as trustees for trusts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">where fifth respondent is potential beneficiary under discretionary trust held: freezing order should be made</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1931">fact that fifth respondent only potential beneficiary and therefore not holder of proprietary interest does not take case outside scope of relevant principles.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">setting aside subpoenas</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">legitimate forensic purpose</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">oppressiveness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">" relating to "</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">costs on an indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">costs payable " forthwith "</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">cross-examination on affidavit as to discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 1147">order for discovery</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">application for costs of interlocutory applications to be made payable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">federal court rules o 62 r 3</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">defendants made late filings of affidavit material causing vacation of trial date</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">costs thrown away</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">final judgment not "far away"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[2008] FCA 952">not appropriate that costs be payable forthwith.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">application by respondent for indemnity costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">where applicant failed to comply with orders of court requiring applicant to file certain documents in preparation for trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">where respondents brought notice of motion seeking orders in relation to applicant's non-compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">where commencement of trial adjourned</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">where applicant's failure to file documents the principal reason for adjournment of trial</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">circumstances in which court may vary ordinary rule as to costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">whether applicant's conduct warrants special order as to costs.  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">application for costs to be paid before conclusion of principal proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">whether appropriate to depart from general rule in o 62, r 3(3). practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">guillotine orders</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">where respondents seek order pursuant to o 35a that proceedings be stayed or dismissed if applicant does not comply with another order of court</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.13" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">whether such order appropriate in circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.14" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">relevant principles.  held: applicant's failure to comply with orders of court do not amount to misconduct</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.15" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">applicant's conduct does not warrant special order as to costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.16" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">costs to be paid on a party and party basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.17" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">no inference that applicant's failure to comply with orders part of a delaying strategy</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.18" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">no reason to order payment of costs before conclusion of principal proceeding</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.19" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">not appropriate circumstances for making of guillotine order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.20" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 903">respondents' application for order pursuant to o 35a dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 906">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCA 906">where substantial delay in proceedings caused by numerous attempts at amending the application and statement of claim, directions hearings have been held which should not have been necessary and interlocutory steps taken and applications brought unnecessarily given the changes to the pleadings.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">trade practices</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">contract, arrangement or understanding within s 4d of the trade practices act 1974 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">vertical agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">horizontal agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">meeting of minds</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">consensus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">knowledge</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">in a series of vertical agreements if no express horizontal agreement whether requirement for necessary implication and agency</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">need to plead offer and acceptance when alleging contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.9" type=cited from="[2004] FCA 571">consent to unlawful term in contract</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 484">category: no</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1347">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1347">application that costs of the respondent's motion for security for costs be payable on an indemnity basis and payable and taxable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 1347">circumstances where the court should exercise its discretion to order that the costs of an interlocutory proceeding be payable and taxable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">springing order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">non-compliance with springing order by first defendant</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">application to extend time for compliance refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">plaintiffs' action against second defendant dismissed by consent</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">subsequent application to extend time for compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.6" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">whether an extension of time would be in the interests of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.7" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 268">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">consideration of appropriate costs order where unsuccessful application for summary judgment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">factors relevant to court's discretion</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">whether costs should be awarded on an indemnity basis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">whether costs to be payable forthwith</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 616">consideration of costs capping</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 364">interlocutory application</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 364">motion to set side orders (including costs order) striking out statement of claim under o 11 r 16 of the federal court rules after filing of amended statement of claim pursuant to o 13 r 3(1) and dismissal of further motion to strike out amended statement of claim</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 364">concurrent application to substitute new orders.  held: motion dismissed; no utility in making orders sought and no prejudice in declining to make them.  costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 364">whether a certificate of taxation should be set aside in circumstances where a party was not entitled to have its bill of costs taxed by reason of o 63 r 3(3) but where taxed costs subsequently paid</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp13.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 364">whether repayment of costs paid under certificate of taxation could be ordered if certificate of taxation is set aside.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.0" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.1" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">springing order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.2" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">non&#173;compliance with springing order</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.3" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">subsequent application to extend time for compliance</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.4" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">whether an extension of time would be in the interests of justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp14.5" type=citing from="[2010] WASC 71">turns on own facts</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">recovery of costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">interlocutory proceedings</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">where costs awarded to one party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">usual rule that not payable forthwith but "in any event"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.6" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">departure from usual rule</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.7" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">no threshold test of exceptional circumstances</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.8" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">order made otherwise where interests of justice require it</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.9" type=citing from="[2009] TASSC 103">whether costs should be payable forthwith.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1190">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1190">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1190">costs in relation to interlocutory applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1190">whether federal magistrates court rules scale applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp16.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1190">whether costs to be paid forthwith.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.0" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1189">human rights</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.1" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1189">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.2" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1189">costs in relation to interlocutory applications</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.3" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1189">whether federal magistrates court rules scale applicable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp17.4" type=citing from="[2009] FMCA 1189">whether costs to be paid forthwith.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 484">Furthermore, I think that the third defendant's costs should be taxed and paid forthwith. The power to make such an order is contained in Order 62 Rule 3(2) of the Federal Court Rules . I considered the relevant principles in Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Limited (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 at [19] - [24]. This is an appropriate case for costs to be taxed and paid forthwith because of the nature of the interlocutory application and the likely delay between now and resolution by Court proceedings (should that be necessary) of the claim with respect to the ABB Grain basis contract. The judgments given in favour of the third defendant resolved those claims against it. I made an order on that application that the third defendant's costs be taxed and paid forthwith. The position now is even stronger because the application in question was an unsuccessful one to set aside the judgments. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2010] FCA 1347">In Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 (" Rafferty "), Besanko J said: 
 
 The general rule serves a number of purposes. First, it avoids multiple taxations in a proceeding. Secondly, it avoids the apparent unfairness which may arise where, at an early stage of a proceeding, a party who is ultimately successful is required to pay costs to a party who is ultimately unsuccessful. Finally, it prevents interlocutory proceedings being used as a weapon to exhaust the financial resources of one of the parties. 
 

 
 
 At the same time, the Court may order that costs be paid forthwith, and the cases suggest that that power may be exercised in circumstances in which there is an element of unreasonableness in the conduct of the unsuccessful party, and it is likely that there will be a long delay between the interlocutory proceeding and the conclusion of the principal proceeding. 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs2" from="[2010] WASC 268">Counsel for the first defendant submitted, in effect, that extra time is required to compel the former solicitors to provide access to the documents in accordance with the principles in Rafferty v Time 2000 . He emphasised the fact that the first defendant's former solicitors had instigated the cessation of their retainer. 
Following a substantial quote from Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 ; (2009) 257 ALR 503 , his Honour continued:
 In my view, the reason advanced for non-compliance is unsatisfactory in the context of this application for the following reasons. First, there is no evidence that at least the prospect of the first defendant's solicitors claiming a lien over the documents was not known to the first defendant, or his solicitors, on 11 December 2009 when programming orders were made for the purposes of bringing the matter to trial, or shortly thereafter. The first defendant's solicitor has not deposed to when he first knew of the claimed lien.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs3" from="[2010] FCA 616">The nature of the power to order that costs be paid forthwith was recently considered by Besanko J in Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (ACN 127 893 270) (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 ; (2009) 257 ALR 503. His Honour ordered the respondents to pay the applicant's costs of a notice of motion but refused to order that the costs be paid forthwith. As to the applicable principles, his Honour said: 
 
 20 The general rule, which is embodied in O 62 r 3(3), is that the costs of an interlocutory proceeding are not to be taxed until the principal proceeding is concluded or until further order.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs4" from="[2010] FCA 364">In Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 ; (2009) 257 ALR 503 at [20] , Besanko J summarised the purposes of the general rule embodied in O 62 r 3(3) of the Rules in the following terms: 
 
 'The general rule, which is embodied in O 62 r 3(3), is that the costs of an interlocutory proceeding are not to be taxed until the principal proceeding is concluded or until further order. The general rule serves a number of purposes. First, it avoids multiple taxations in a proceeding. Second, it avoids the apparent unfairness which may arise where, at an early stage of a proceeding, a party who is ultimately successful is required to pay costs to a party who is ultimately unsuccessful. Finally, it prevents interlocutory proceedings being used as a weapon to exhaust the financial resources of one of the parties. ' 
 

 </sentence>
<sentence id="cs5" from="[2010] WASC 71">21 He says that his present solicitor wrote to his former solicitors by letter dated 31 March 2010 seeking the release of the documents, and referring to a Federal Court decision in relation to liens, namely, Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 ; (2009) 257 ALR 503. I note that this was the first occasion on which the first defendant's solicitor wrote to obtain the release of the documents from the first defendant's former solicitors. This was nearly three weeks after the expiration of the time for compliance with order 1 of the springing orders. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs6" from="[2009] TASSC 103">The discretion to order "otherwise" is unfettered. The Rules are silent as to when costs are payable, in the case of an order being made "otherwise", and given to one party . 13 As to the rationale of the rule, in Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Limited (No 3) [2009] FCA 727 ; (2009) 257 ALR 503 , at 508 [20], Besanko J set out three purposes which it served. His Honour said:
 
 
 "First, it avoids multiple taxations in a proceeding. Secondly, it avoids the apparent unfairness which may arise where, at an early stage of a proceeding, a party who is ultimately successful is required to pay costs to a party who is ultimately unsuccessful.</sentence>
<sentence id="cs7" from="[2009] FMCA 1190">In Rafferty and Others v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (ACN 127 893 270) and Others (No 3) (2009) 257 ALR 503 ; [2009] FCA 727 an application for an order to pay costs of an interlocutory application forthwith was refused. Relevantly, Besanko J set out the advantages of the general rule embodied in O.62 r.3(3) (at [20]). The general principles referred to are relevant in this case. I am not persuaded that there can be said to be such an element of unreasonableness in the conduct of the unsuccessful party at this stage of the proceedings or that it is likely that there will be such a delay between the interlocutory proceeding and the conclusion of the principal proceeding that the costs should be payable forthwith. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs8" from="[2009] FMCA 1189">In Rafferty and Others v Time 2000 West Pty Ltd (ACN 127 893 270) and Others (No 3) (2009) 257 ALR 503 ; [2009] FCA 727 an application for an order to pay costs of an interlocutory application forthwith was refused. Relevantly, Besanko J set out the advantages of the general rule embodied in O.62 r.3(3) (at [20]). The general principles referred to are relevant in this case. I am not persuaded that there can be said to be such an element of unreasonableness in the conduct of the unsuccessful party at this stage of the proceedings or that it is likely that there will be such a delay between the interlocutory proceeding and the conclusion of the principal proceeding that the costs should be payable forthwith. </sentence>
<sentence id="cs9" from="[2009] FCA 782">While very often an order for costs in an interlocutory application merges, in practical effect, with the costs of the proceedings, this case is one where, in my opinion, costs ought be ordered to be payable forthwith: see McKellar v Container Terminal Management Services Limited [1999] FCA 1639 at [13] and following, and more recent cases collected in Rafferty v Time 2000 West Pty Limited (No 3) [2009] FCA 727.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l1">TRADE PRACTICES (INDUSTRY CODES -- FRANCHISING) REGULATIONS 1998 </title>
</legistitles>
</case>