<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Australian Competition &amp; Consumer Commission v StoresOnline International Inc [2009] FCA 717 (6 July 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/717.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 467">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 467">whether evidence of two witnesses should be taken by use of audio visual facilities</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 467">relevant considerations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2004] NSWSC 467">whether, in the alternative, orders should be made for the issue of a letter of request to the competent judicial authority in the united kingdom for the examination of the witnesses before the trial judge as examiner</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 107">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 107">application for videoconferencing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 107">two witnesses based in new zealand</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 107">required for cross-examination</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 107">application granted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">whether hearsay evidence of statements by persons overseas should be permitted</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">the extent to which the proposed evidence was first hand or more remote hearsay</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">no independent evidence corroborating any hearsay version</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">whether undue prejudice to the respondent.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">application to take evidence by video link</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">requirement to make out a case for such an order where it is opposed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">discussion of the possible difficulties associated with video evidence.   practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">security for costs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=citing from="[2009] FCA 1306">consideration of application for further security.</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 107">Instances can be provided where, in the exercise of the discretion conferred by s 47A(1) , evidence has been permitted to be given by way of video link: eg, Reinsurance Australia Corporation Ltd v HIH Casualty &amp; General Insurance Ltd (in liq) [2002] FCA 1549. In Sheldon &amp; Hammond Pty Ltd v Metrokane Inc [2002] FCA 1561 , Conti J permitted evidence to be given by way of video link where a witness was too ill to travel to Sydney. Instances can also be cited where there has emerged a reason for requiring a witness to attend in court in person. In Dorajay Pty Ltd v Aristocrat Leisure Ltd [2007] FCA 1502 , for example, leave was refused in circumstances where the estimated cross-examination was lengthy. In Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v StonesOnline International Inc [2009] FCA 717 , leave was also refused where the use of a video link facility was opposed and where there was ( inter alia ) anticipated difficulty in cross-examining by way of video link. Similarly, perhaps, in Campaign Master (UK) Ltd v Forty Two International Pty Ltd (No 3) [2009] FCA 1306 at [78] , [2009] FCA [2009] FCA 1306 ; 1306 ; 181 FCR 152 at 171 Buchanan J stated that he did " not share the view expressed by Katz J ". </sentence>
<sentence id="cs1" from="[2009] FCA 1306">Some cases have suggested that any apparent tension between the two streams of authority I have identified is readily enough reconciled upon the facts of a particular case (see Australian Competition and Consumer Commission v StoresOnline International Inc [2009] FCA 717 , per Edmonds J citing Austin J in Australian Securities and Investments Commissioner v Rich [2004] NSWSC 467 ; (2004) 49 ACSR 578 (at [19], [22], [28], [31] and [43]). Edmonds J said (at [14]) that the observations of Austin J: 
 
 14 ... illustrate the point that the choice in every case cannot be determined solely by reference to general principles because it is the application of those principles to the facts and circumstances of the particular case which must determine the choice; in the circumstances of a particular case, a matter may point one way and in another case it may point another way. At the end of the day, the exercise of the discretion as to what is appropriate in a particular case will involve a balancing exercise as to what will best serve the administration of justice consistently with maintaining justice between the parties: see Giles CJ in Sunstate Airlines at [4]. 
 

 </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l1">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 47A Testimony by video link, audio link or other appropriate means</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 47C Conditions for use of video links, audio links or other appropriate means</title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>