<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>Commissioner of Taxation v Barnes Development Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 830 (7 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/830.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">bluebottle uk limited v deputy commissioner of taxation  taxes and duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">income tax and related legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">collection and recovery of tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">collection of tax due and payable by a non-resident from a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">two non-resident shareholders in virgin blue holdings limited ("virgin blue") allegedly derived income or profits or gains of a capital nature from a source in australia</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">directors of virgin blue declared a dividend due for payment on 15 december 2005 to those who were shareholders on a specified record date of 28 november 2005</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.6" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">after the record date but before the date for payment of the dividend, the deputy commissioner of taxation ("the commissioner") issued notices to virgin blue pursuant to s 255 of the income tax assessment act 1936 (cth) ("the act ") purporting to require virgin blue to retain an amount from the dividend owed to each shareholder to meet the shareholder's tax liability</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.7" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">the following day, which was before the date for payment of the dividend, the shareholders agreed to assign their rights to the dividend to a third party and informed virgin blue of that agreement</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.8" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">the following day, which was still before the date for payment of the dividend, the commissioner issued tax assessment notices to the shareholders and further notices to virgin blue pursuant to s 255 of the act</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.9" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">whether virgin blue was required to retain the dividend to pay the shareholders' tax liability.  taxes and duties</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.10" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">income tax and related legislation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.11" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">whether s 255 of the act required the commissioner to assess a non-resident's tax liability before the commissioner could require a third party to pay the tax due and payable by that non-resident</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.12" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">relevance of relationship between s 218 and s 255 of the act .  corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.13" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">share capital</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.14" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">shares</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.15" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">dividends</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.16" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">assignment of rights to receive a dividend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.17" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">whether a shareholder could assign its rights to receive a dividend to a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.18" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">whether a corporation was bound to recognise a shareholder's assignment of its rights to receive a dividend to a third party</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.19" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">relevance of statutory contract under s 140(1) of the corporations act 2001 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.20" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">time at which virgin blue incurred a "debt" to its shareholders in respect of the dividend</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.21" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">relevance of distinction between declaring a dividend and determining that a dividend is payable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.22" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">relevance of "record date".  equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.23" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">assignments in equity</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.24" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 54">whether the shareholders' agreement to assign the rights to the dividend purported to effect an equitable assignment or a statutory assignment pursuant to s 199 of the property law act 1974 (q).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.0" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.1" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">natural justice</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.2" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">criminal justice commission</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.3" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">requirement to report to parliamentary committee, speaker of legislative assembly and minister</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.4" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">report on gaming machine concerns and regulations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.5" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">recommendation to exclude certain persons from gaming machine industry in state</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.6" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">no opportunity given to answer matters raised in reports</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.7" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">whether duty of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.8" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">whether right or interest adversely affected</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.9" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">legitimate expectation</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.10" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">mandamus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.11" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">certiorari</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.12" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">declaration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.13" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">criminal justice act 1989 (q.), ss 2.1(1), 2.14, 2.15, 2.18, 3.17, 3.21(2)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp3.14" type=cited from="[1992] HCA 10">gaming machine act 1991 (q.), s. 6.16(1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">certiorari</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">privative clause</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">error of law on face of record</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">decision of tribunal not liable to be challenged, appealed against, reviewed, quashed or called in question by any court on any account whatsoever</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.4" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">whether review by certiorari for error of law on face of record excluded</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.5" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.6" type=cited from="[1982] HCA 2">industrial arbitration act 1940-1981 (n.s.w.), s. 84(1).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">income tax (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">recovery of tax</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">statutory garnishee</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">notice to taxpayer's bank</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">term deposits</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">terms unexpired</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">notice served before tax payable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">when tax "due"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">debts purportedly assigned before tax payable</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">whether money due or accruing due to taxpayer</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">whether service of notice prevents such assignment</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">"equities"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[1981] HCA 40">income tax assessment act 1936 (cth), s. 218(1)(a)(i).</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">corporations</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">rights of access to books and financial records by director</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">where director seeking inspection by his agents</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">whether granting access to documents would impede receiver in realising assets on behalf of the appointor</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">right of inspection at common or general law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.5" type=citing from="[2011] FCA 609">corporations act 2001 (cth) s 198f , s 290(2) , s 421 and s 1303</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2011] FCA 609">Projections such as budgets, trial balances or business plans, prime entries in cash books and journals, documents used to facilitate the preparation or auditing of annual or half yearly financial statements, documents which keep track of matters such as sales, cost of sales, cash, debtors, creditors and banking and financial arrangements and liquidator's reports: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Rich [2005] NSWSC 417 ; [2005] NSWSC 417 ; (2005) 216 ALR 320. Profit and loss statements, balance sheets, financial reports, bank statements, equity loan agreements with investors, share certificates issued by capital and deeds of release in furtherance of rollover transactions, provisional liquidator's reports and liquidator's reports, tracing spreadsheets: Australian Securities and Investments Commission v Sydney Investment House Equities Pty Ltd [2008] NSWSC 1224 ; (2008) 69 ACSR 1. Loan accounts and journal entries in general and ledger: Commissioner of Taxation v Barnes Development Pty Ltd [2009] FCA 830. Loan contract including its financial information: CBA v Marwan Tabet [2008] VSC 161. General ledgers, trial balances and books incorporating the journal entries made to prepare or finalise the financial statements: Haines v Altarcoo Pastoral [2009] NSWSC 214.</sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 </title>
<title id="l1">CORPORATIONS ACT 2001 - SECT 1305 Admissibility of books in evidence</title>
<title id="l2">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 </title>
<title id="l3">FEDERAL COURT OF AUSTRALIA ACT 1976 - SECT 51A Interest up to judgment</title>
<title id="l4">INCOME TAX ASSESSMENT ACT 1936 </title>
<title id="l5">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 </title>
<title id="l6">TAXATION ADMINISTRATION ACT 1953 - SECT 5 Tenure of Commissioner and Second Commissioners</title>
<title id="l7">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
</legistitles>
</case>