<?xml version="1.0"?>
<case>
<name>SZFQY v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 935 (24 August 2009)</name>
<AustLII>http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/FCA/2009/935.html</AustLII>
<citphrases>
<citphrase id="cp0.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">appeal from judgment of federal magistrate</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">application seeking judicial review of decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">whether refugee review tribunal failed to afford the applicant procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">applicant raised new issue during review tribunal hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">refugee review tribunal told applicant it would consider corroborative evidence submitted after the hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">whether s 425 of the migration act 1958 (cth) required the refugee review tribunal to afford the applicant a further hearing</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp0.7" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 83">whether rejection of corroborative evidence by the refugee review tribunal was information within the meaning of s 424a of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">application for review of decision of refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">whether tribunal erred in failing to provide appellant with particulars of information relating to a document provided to the appellant in a s 424a letter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">court must determine objectively what the tribunal considered was the reason or part of the reason for affirming the decision under review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">s 424a of the migration act 1958 (cth) cannot be interpreted as imposing an obligation not found to exist on the proper construction of that section</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp1.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 712">appeal dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 596">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 596">failure by tribunal to disclose to appellant source of information put to him at tribunal hearing did not breach s 424a of migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp2.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCA 596">no breach of s 424a where information supplied by a third party to the tribunal which contradicted appellant's evidence was of no dispositive relevance to tribunal's decision.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.0" type=cited from="[2009] FMCA 395">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.1" type=cited from="[2009] FMCA 395">review of decision of rrt</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.2" type=cited from="[2009] FMCA 395">where applicant alleged jurisdictional error in the tribunal's failure to discuss with him independent country information</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp4.3" type=cited from="[2009] FMCA 395">where applicant alleged tribunal had not considered corroborating documents.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.0" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.1" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">interpretation of s 424aa of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.2" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">whether failure on the part of the refugee review tribunal to comply with s 424aa once it chooses to provide oral particulars of information at a review hearing constitutes jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.3" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">the tribunal has a discretion whether or not to invoke the provisions of s 424aa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.4" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">a decision not to invoke s 424aa or non-compliance with the requirements of that section once invoked does not amount to jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.5" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">obiter dicta to the contrary by driver fm in szltc v minister for immigration and citizenship [2008] fmca 384 not followed and disapproved</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.6" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">whether country information is information within the meaning of s 424aa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.7" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">country information not information within s 424aa</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.8" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">in the instant case the tribunal complied with s 424aa in any event</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.9" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">the tribunal was not obliged to consider the " what if i'm wrong test " (as to which see minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v rajalingam [1999] fca 719 ; (1999) 93 fcr 220)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.10" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">for this reason, error in the application of that test would not matter</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.11" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">the tribunal's conclusions in respect of relocation were an independent and additional basis for its decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp5.12" type=cited from="[2009] FCAFC 46">appeal dismissed</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 198">1 in the reasons for judgment of the honourable justices dowsett, bennett and edmonds jj delivered today: in para 2, line 4</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 198">delete "livedg7" and replace with "lived"; 2 in the reasons for judgment of the honourable justices dowsett, bennett and edmonds jj delivered today: in para 21, line 3</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 198">delete "the section provides:" and replace with "the section at the relevant date provided:". 3 in the reasons for judgment of the honourable justices dowsett, bennett and edmonds jj delivered today: in para 21</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp6.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCAFC 198">delete the quoted section in its entirety and replace with the following:</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.0" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2046">administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.1" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2046">requirements of procedural fairness</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.2" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2046">procedural fairness does not require the disclosure to a party before an administrative tribunal of the manner in which particular material may be used</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.3" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2046">procedural fairness does not require disclosure of the evolving process of deliberation or decision-making</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp7.4" type=cited from="[2007] FCA 2046">veal v minister for immigration and multicultural and indigenous affairs [2005] hca 72 does not impose any general requirement upon an administrative decision maker to disclose all prior facts and knowledge, of which he may be aware by reason of his having been involved in earlier cases, where relevant to the particular matters now at issue</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.0" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">szbyr v minister for immigration and citizenship  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.1" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.2" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the appellants were refused a visa under s 36(2) of the migration act 1958 (cth) ("the act ")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.3" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the appellants gave a statutory declaration to the refugee review tribunal ("the tribunal")</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.4" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">the tribunal affirmed the decision not to grant a visa partly on the basis of discrepancies between the statutory declaration and the appellants' oral evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.5" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether relief was available to the appellants.  immigration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.6" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">refugees</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.7" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">s 424a of the act , read with s 441a , requires that an applicant be given written notice of particulars of any information that would be a reason or a part of the reason for affirming a decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.8" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether s 424a applied to the appellants' statutory declaration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.9" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">temporal scope of s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.10" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether the tribunal breached s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.11" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether the tribunal committed jurisdictional error</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.12" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">meaning of "information"</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.13" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether "information" included discrepancies or inadequacies in previously submitted evidence</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.14" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">meaning of "reason, or a part of the reason".  administrative law</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.15" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">constitutional writs</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.16" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">certiorari and mandamus</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.17" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">impact of discretionary considerations governing availability of relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp9.18" type=cited from="[2007] HCA 26">whether relief should be denied on discretionary grounds for lack of a convention nexus.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.0" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">practice and procedure</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.1" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">circumstances in which a later full court can depart from an earlier full court decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.2" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">stare decisis</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.3" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">determining ratio decidendi</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.4" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">application of minister for immigration and multicultural affairs v al shamry (2001) 110 fcr 27  migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.5" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">the application of s 424a(1) of the migration act 1958 (cth)</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp10.6" type=cited from="[2006] FCAFC 2">meaning of 'application', 'information', and 'reason, or part of the reason' in s 424a</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.0" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 92">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.1" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 92">appeal from a decision of a judge of the federal court dismissing an application for judicial review of a decision of the refugee review tribunal</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.2" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 92">whether s 424a(3)(a) of the migration act 1958 (cth) required the tribunal to draw the applicant's attention to country information that was not specifically relevant to him</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp11.3" type=cited from="[2005] FCAFC 92">appeal dismissed.</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.0" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.1" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">application for protection visa refused</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.2" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">tribunal's understanding of the word 'persecution'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.3" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">s 424a of migration act 1958</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.4" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">whether information was 'the reason or part of the reason' for affirming the decision under review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.5" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">meaning of 'information'</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.6" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">identification of the 'reason' for decision</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.7" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">an interpretative task</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp12.8" type=cited from="[2004] FCAFC 123">discretionary ground to refuse relief</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.0" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">migration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.1" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">alleged failure to allow sufficient time to answer questions</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.2" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">alleged failure to allow adjournments of sufficient duration</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.3" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">onus of proof</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.4" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">importance of understanding why information relevant to review</citphrase>
<citphrase id="cp15.5" type=citing from="[2010] FCA 105">onus of establishing ground of review</citphrase>
</citphrases>
<citances>
<sentence id="cs0" from="[2010] FCA 105">The evolution of s 424A and the introduction of s 424AA have been recounted by Tracey and Foster JJ in SZMCD v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship ( 'SZMCD' ) [2009] FCAFC 46 at [63] to [70] [2009] FCAFC 46 ; [2009] FCAFC 46 ; , 174 FCR 415 at 429 to 430. After having done so, their Honours observed: 
 
 [71] The policy and purpose reflected in s 424A is that the Tribunal should be compelled: 
 
 
 
 
 (a) To put the visa applicant on fair notice in writing of critical matters of concern to the Tribunal;
 (b) To ensure that the visa applicant understands the significance of those matters to the decision under review; and
 (c) To give the applicant a reasonable opportunity to comment on or to respond to those matters of concern. 
 
 

 
 
 [72] It is evident that the same policy and purpose underpin s 424AA. 
 

 
 Sections 424A and 424AA " are intended to be complementary ": SZMCD [2009] FCAFC 46 at [2] , [2009] FCAFC 46 ; 174 FCR 415 at 417 per Moore J. See also: SZFQY v Minister for Immigration and Citizenship [2009] FCA 935 at [31] . </sentence>
</citances>
<legistitles>
<title id="l0">MIGRATION ACT 1958 </title>
<title id="l1">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 422B Exhaustive statement of natural justice hearing rule</title>
<title id="l2">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424A Information and invitation given in writing by Tribunal</title>
<title id="l3">MIGRATION ACT 1958 - SECT 424AA Information and invitation given orally by Tribunal while applicant appearing</title>
<title id="l4">MIGRATION LEGISLATION AMENDMENT ACT (NO. 1) 1998 </title>
<title id="l5">FEDERAL COURT RULES </title>
<title id="l6">MIGRATION AMENDMENT (REVIEW PROVISIONS) ACT 2007 (NO. 100, 2007) </title>
</legistitles>
</case>